Hi, good morning everyone. It's the 5th of אדר, Adar, the 20th
of February, and today's דף Daf is going to be עבודה זרה
ל"ו. Avodah Zarah Lamed Vav. We're on the last line of ל"ה
עמוד ב'. Lamed Hey Amud Bet. My name is Dan Margulies and
I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer while he is in Israel. So
the next topic of our משנה Mishna was the question of the
כשרות, kashrut, the permissibility of the oil produced by idolaters, and the
משנה Mishna had said, ושמן שלהם, v'hashemen shelahem, and their oil, and
then had continued, רבי ובית דינו התירו השמן, Rabbi u'veit dino hitiru
hashemen,
that רבי Rabbi and his בית דין, Beit Din, that is in
the time the משנה Mishna was being authored in the second century,
permitted the oil, that is at some point there had been a
prohibition against oil, and then it became permissible later. So we're going
to see the discussion first of when was oil made prohibited because
it's a rabbinic גזירה. gezeira. We have to, we want to know
when it was first instituted, and then we want to understand why
and when was it repealed. This is one of the more interesting
examples, as far as I know, is one of the rather few
examples of a rabbinic גזירה gezeira which was repealed. There are a
number of them which were mentioned throughout ש"ס, Shas, but this is
one of sort of the most prominent, and therefore it becomes an
important test case for understanding the scope and parameters.
Other ones were mentioned? A lot of ones in טומאה וטהרה Tumat
ve'Tahara I think, certain ones were repealed also. Off the top of
my head I can't think of an example. Glass?
Glass is something else, but anyway...
Are we going to talk about מוקצה muktzeh or milk?
Oh right, you want me to answer the cheese question. Basically from
the סוגיא Sugya that was studied yesterday, which I think has like
seven different answers to the cheese question, why was the cheese made
prohibited? I will note, by the way, the entire discussion is not
"is cheese prohibited" but "why was cheese made prohibited," that is, presumably
the law is that the cheese was prohibited, therefore you have to
get the kosher cheese. תוספות's Tosafot's conclusion from that סוגיא Sugya seems
to be the position of what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi who said the snake venom is the problem and it's
a problem of סכנה. sakana. And then by making it a problem
of סכנה, sakana, you set yourself up for, "oh, but we know
that many of the things which if they're prohibited because of סכנה,
sakana, maybe if we can demonstrably prove that the סכנה sakana is
no longer a risk, then maybe it won't be a problem," at
least according to those opinions who think that, not everyone thinks
that. People do actually say that?
People
do try to פוסק pasken like תוספות, Tosafot, and some people try
to argue even maybe the רמ"א Rama פוסק paskens like תוספות, Tosafot,
maybe the חזון איש Chazon Ish פוסק paskens like תוספות, Tosafot, maybe
רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik פוסק paskens like תוספות Tosafot in different circumstances.
Certainly the רמב"ם Rambam and many of the more prominent other ראשונים
Rishonim take the bent that the reason is the reason because of
the נבילה nevela or קיבה, keva, the stomach lining that or the
rennet that they use is derived from נבילה, nevela, and therefore it's
a problem.
Wait, is it the stomach lining or is it the rennet?
Because those are two different things, right? One is פרש, peresh, the
other is... So in this case, it's from the stomach itself, which
is a real piece of meat, but that the rennet is extracted
from the stomach skin of the stomach or whatever it is. But
the עור קיבה or keva that's used for the curdling of the
milk was a problem of נבילה, nevela, and that the נבילה nevela
will be a problem as absorbed, the taste of נבילה nevela will
be absorbed into the cheese, and because it's a מאמיד ma'amid and
all these other kind of things, it won't be בטל, batel, and
that will be that sort of would be the risk, at least,
which is why even if we're concerned
that that דאורייתא d'oraishah problem doesn't exist, the rabbis made a דרבנן
d'rabanan decree against all cheeses produced by non-Jewish producers because of that
reason.
How is it done today?
How is it done today? Many cheeses use a rennet which is
derived from a microbial source, which some people would try to argue
maybe doesn't even fall into the גזירה gezeira at all. That was
a debate in the גאונים Geonic times about a vegetable-derived curdling agents
like those from the sap of the fig trees and things like
that. And that's there, it's quoted, both opinions are quoted in the
רמב"ם Rambam interestingly enough, and if you look there, there's an extensive
debate in the ראשונים Rishonim about if it comes from a vegetable
source. So here too it seems like that becomes that debate. רמב"ם
Rambam and many of the גאונים Geonim were מחמיר, machmir, but it
certainly was not something that's explicitly addressed in the תלמוד, Talmud, leaves
open the room there as well.
Wait, so basically what I'm understanding today is... Well there's no, I
mean presumably there's no snake venom concern. Right. And then if it's
done from a totally different process then...
because maybe it's still, maybe the definition of the cheese making process
is still that it's that's considered a curdling process that the תלמוד
Talmud defined as cheese and it falls under the penumbra of that
גזירה. gezeira. That's a debate between the ראשונים, Rishonim, you could see
it in the, I forget which פרק perek it is in מאכלות
אסורות, Ma'achalot Asurot, but it's right there where he's talking about the
cheese. He talks about the fig sap curdled cheeses and he said
oh even in a case where it's obvious in the texture of
the cheese that it was produced this way, it's still a debate
and קל וחומר kal vachomer if it's sort of... unidentifiable which way
it was produced. So certainly the רמב״ם's Rambam position, I would say,
is the normative one and certainly is the one which is more
מחמיר. machmir. But anyway, let's continue with the שמן. shemen. We have
an interesting back to bread, right? What? The bread comes through the
oil discussion as well. So we're going to see that. השמן שלהם,
Hashemen shelahem, their oil. שמן, Shemen, regarding oil, רב אמר, Rav amar,
רב's Rav position is דניאל גזר עליו, Daniel gazar alav, that in
the period of דניאל, Daniel, דניאל Daniel is not considered a נביא
navi exactly in our tradition, but he's something close to a נביא.
navi. So he and his בית דין Beit Din during the period
of the exile made this rabbinic decree against using oil produced by
non-Jews. ושמואל אמר, uShmuel amar, זליפתן של כלים טמאים אוסרתן. zelifatan shel
keilim tmeiyim osartan. שמואל Shmuel says it's the seepage, the extraction of
טמא tamei substances which were absorbed into the כלים keilim which is
a problem. I'm confused.
I thought it's you press it in the whatever, your vat, then
you
put it in like these big jars. Right, you put it in
a jar, but what if the jar was already טמא? tamei? And
so the oil will go in and it'll become, it'll extract some
amount of liquid which was already in, absorbed into the jar which
was טמא, tamei, it'll make the oil טמא. tamei. So we're going
to have a question.
I'm saying they do put it in or were maybe they do,
in which case then maybe they whatever, maybe they whatever anything you
could say maybe.
שמואל's Shmuel statement sounds like
100%. זליפתן של כלים טמאים אוסרתן. Zelifatan shel keilim tmeiyim osartan. The
fact that there is seepage of טמא tamei liquids from these כלים
keilim makes them prohibited. But the גמרא Gemara asks a question on
שמואל's Shmuel position and says: אטו כולי עלמא אוכלי טהרות נינהו? Atu
kulei alma ochlei taharot ninhu? Is everyone someone who eats only
חולין chullin foods in a state of טהרה? tahara? That is, this
is not a requirement, this is a מידת חסידות, midat chasidut, this
is some kind of a חומרא chumra which
many people, many of the rabbinic class in the time of the
משנה Mishna at least held to, but it doesn't, it's not mandatory,
at least it doesn't seem
mandatory. אלא זליפתן של כלים אסורים אוסרתן. Ela zelifatan shel keilim assurim
osartan. Rather, it's a seepage of prohibited jars. That is, imagine you
had a jar that had absorbed
lard or had absorbed non-kosher wine or something like that, and then
you would put the olive oil in the jar, it would absorb
the flavor. I would think they wouldn't want to do
that,
cause that degrades the quality of the oil. You're anticipating the גמרא.
Gemara. We're going to learn the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. אמר ליה שמואל
לרב. Amar lei Shmuel leRav. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel says to רב,
Rav, בשלמא לדידי דאמינא זליפתן של כלים אסורים אוסרתן. Bishlama ledidi de'amina
zelifatan shel keilim assurim osartan. I understand my own position because I
say it's because the flavor of the prohibited foods is going to
make the oil
prohibited. היינו דכי אתא רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא ואמר דרש
רבי סימלאי בנציבין שמן רבי יהודה ובית דינו נמנו
עליו והתירוהו. Hainu dechi ata Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta ve'amar
darash Rabi Simlai beNtzivin shemen Rabi Yehuda uVeit Dino nimnu alav vehitiruhu.
Meaning שמואל Shmuel says my reasoning makes sense for why it would
have been prohibited at one point and then they would have reassessed
the situation and determined to make it permitted. That is, why? Because
the position of
רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta
who said that it was רבי סימלאי Rabi Simlai who taught in
נציבין Ntzivin that when רבי יהודה, Rabi Yehuda, that is רבי יהודה
הנשיא, Rabi Yehuda HaNasi, and his בית דין Beit Din counted, they
voted about the
oil, נמנו עליו והתירוהו, nimnu alav vehitiruhu, they voted to permit it.
Why was their reasoning for permitting it? קסבר נותן טעם לפגם מותר.
Kasavar noten ta'am lifgam mutar. Because their position, or they had reassessed
or they had clarified, that if it's a case where the flavor
which would be imparted will be a negative, detrimental flavor, then it's
permissible. So if you're going to have olive oil that has the
taste from wine in the same jars or something like that, they're
going to say oh, but that actually ruins the flavor of the
olive oil, so it's not going to be a halachic problem, we're
not concerned about that, we're not going to make this rabbinic decree
about this concern because it's... So does that mean before their time
there wasn't such a הלכה halacha of
נותן טעם לפגם מותר noten ta'am lifgam mutar or not, or how
it was applied, or whether or not they reassessed whether or not
the flavor that would be transferred to the oil would be נותן
טעם לפגם noten ta'am lifgam or not? These are all important questions
to ask about our גמרא. Gemara. אלא לדידך, Ela ledidach, but yeah...
They continually insert here in their own edition that whenever they're referring
to דניאל, Daniel, it's because of his concern about intermarriage.
Oh, we're going to see. Intermarriage is going to come up later.
We haven't even got to the דניאל Daniel question yet, right? This
is still שמואל. Shmuel. So שמואל Shmuel was defending his own position,
that is it was about the flavor of the
non-kosher adulterant that was seeping into the oil. But now he says:
אלא לדידך דאמרת דניאל גזר עליו. Ela ledidach de'amarta Daniel gazar alav.
For you, רב, Rav, if you say that it was דניאל Daniel
who made the law against it, that is רב's Rav position. One
second.
So
you're saying he's not viewed as a נביא? navi? What is he
viewed as?
He's viewed as a דניאל. Daniel. I don't
know. I don't have one of those. Okay. אלא לדידך דאמרת דניאל
גזר עליו דניאל גזר ואתא רבי יהודה הנשיא ומבטל ליה? Ela ledidach
de'amarta Daniel gazar alav Daniel gazar ve'ata Rabi Yehuda HaNasi umvattel lei?
Are you really going to tell me that a הלכה halacha that
דניאל Daniel had instituted centuries before, which was well-established
It says דניאל ובית דינו.
Daniel u-veit dino. We're going to see that's going to come up
as well how much was this a personal חומרא chumra of Daniel's
or how much was this actually a law that he had instituted
with his בית דין. Beit Din. It says דניאל ובית דינו? Daniel
u-veit dino? Maybe I missed it. שמואל אמר... Shmuel amar... sorry רב
אמר Rav amar דניאל גזר על... Daniel gazar al... Okay fine, it
doesn't say דניאל ובית דינו. Daniel u-veit dino. I'm reading that in
because that's how my... you're right. It's a... it's a...
Right, but meaning,
right, so that's going to be discussed, but it comes up later
about the בית דין, Beit Din, I think. But part of it
is also that's sort of just how I've been wired to think,
but you're right, it's not actually in the גמרא.
Gemara. Right. That's what I'm trying to say. I mean it's different
if like, you know, he's like "Ah, yeah, I really think... you're
a prominent figure in the society, like, you know, this is what
I think we should be doing" is different than saying, "Alright, let's
get a בית דין Beit Din together, let's get all the leading,
you know, גדולי הדור gedolei ha-dor of the generation and like פסקן
pasken it." Right, exactly.
Well, that's for sure it's different. Well, that's what's going to come
up here. At least for now, the assumption is that it was
a גזירה gezeira that Daniel had instituted, it was a real promulgated
law, and שמואל Shmuel is saying, "Yeah, and if it was a
real law, then how could רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi come
along and repeal it?" Okay, because we have the principle
והתנן אין בית דין יכול לבטל דברי בית דין חבירו אלא אם
כן גדול הימנו בחכמה ובמנין. ve-hatnan ein beit din yakhol levatel divrei
beit din chavero ela im ken gadol heimenu be-chokhma u-ve-minyan. That the
general principle for רבני rabbinic decrees, and this is discussed much in
the first פרק perek of ביצה, Beitza, that is, if one court,
one בית דין... Beit Din... now there are two different ways we
could read this. One way to read this is...
one
local בית דין Beit Din made a certain local ruling, and then
another local בית דין Beit Din of the same standing, like the,
you know, the, you know, the United States Court of Appeals, District
One and United States District... District Two Court of Appeals can't overrule
each other because they're not either one
גדול ממנו בחכמה ומנין. gadol mimenu be-chokhma u-minyan. That is, they each
have their own jurisdiction and the only way to overrule a decree
of a lower court is to appeal it to a higher court.
It would have to go to the Supreme Court, it would have
to go to the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. That's one way to read it.
They can't overrule themselves, right?
The other... right, so and that would assume that the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
in any generation has the power to reassess or redefine decrees from
earlier סנהדרין. Sanhedrins. But that doesn't fit what's being discussed here. It
sounds like what's being discussed here... David, I'll take your question a
second. What sounds like being discussed here is that in a later
stage of history, the High Court cannot repeal laws made by an
earlier High Court. The Supreme Court issues a certain ruling, it sets
a precedent, it sets the דין דרבנן, din d'rabbanan, and once that's
in effect, then a later סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, a later High Court, cannot
repeal it unless they have גדול הימנו בחכמה, gadol heimenu be-chokhma, they're
smarter, they're better educated, I don't know exactly how you would assess
that, ובמנין, u-ve-minyan, and they have more... sounds like more members. Yeah,
I understand that, so it has to be more members. It's also
strange, because certainly it seems like the סנהדרין Sanhedrin normally was always
71 members, except for
אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset HaGedolah. The עזרא'ס... עזרא'ס בית דין Ezra's...
Ezra's Beit Din and perhaps this is why the laws that עזרא
Ezra made could not be repealed, is because
עזרא'ס בית דין Ezra's Beit Din is 120, not 70. That's a...
another possibility. Alternatively, במנין... be-minyan... 120 vs 23, right?
And then it was overruled by the court of 71...
well, but that's the point is that if we're talking about בית
דין Beit Din with a capital ב bet and a capital ד,
dalet, we're talking about בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol that's in
Jerusalem, that that would be... so then it has to be talking
about a later stage in history, can they reassess the rulings of
an earlier סנהדרין? Sanhedrin?
Well, they made it for a reason then they can't...
Right, so... okay. The other piece is מנין minyan could refer not
to the number of members of the court, but מנין minyan could
refer to the number of students that they have. That is, or
the amount of influence or the amount of jurisdiction that they have.
If they have a larger constituency, if they have a larger number
of students, they're considered more authoritative or more... their rulings are more
binding because more people follow them.
How do you define that word?
That's a creative... it is a creative read but it's discussed like
I said, it's discussed in the ראשונים Rishonim and it's a principle
which is worth spending a lot of time understanding because it really
lies at the heart of how do we understand דינים דרבנן. dinim
d'rabbanan. Yeah.
They reprinted עדיות, Eduyot, the first chapter... עדיות... Eduyot... I said it's...
so עדיות Eduyot is just the משנה. Mishna. In the גמרא Gemara
in ביצה Beitza in the first chapter, basically everything about דינים דרבנן
dinim d'rabbanan is discussed in ביצה Beitza in the first
chapter. Okay. אמר ליה סימלאי לודאה כהאמרת? Amar lei Simlai Luda'ah ke-ha'amarta?
Are you telling me that this is the principle that was articulated
by סימלאי Simlai from
לוד? Lod?
Okay. Simlai from
Lod, okay. דקאמרת שאני לודאי דמזלזלו, De-ka'amarta shani Luda'ei de-mizalzelu, but people
from לוד Lod are generally lax with their observance of the rabbinic
decrees, so we can't take their opinion seriously. Okay. I'm sorry, what...
which one over here?
That is if... so שמואל Shmuel says back to רב, Rav, right,
רב Rav had said... the principle was Daniel and we said oh
and if it was Daniel who had decreed it then Rebbi's בית
דין Beis Din had to overrule it and Shmuel is challenging Rav
and Shmuel said wait a second isn't there a principle
of בית דין יכול לבטל דברי בית דין חברו Beis Din yachol
levatel divrei Beis Din chaveiro that that Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi's בית דין
Beis Din would not have enough jurisdiction or legal power to overrule
Daniel because they were not presumably greater in חכמה ומנין chochma u'minyan
okay
and so and then they say but is that really sort of
that position that you're adopting that's quoted to you by
שמלאי Simlai from לוד Lod and the people from לוד Lod generally
have a reputation of being lax with their interpretations or application of
rabbinic law such that we can't really trust
his application of that principle to this case okay that's Rav defending
himself
so this is a rabbi's being accused of being lax in observance
or lax in how they consider the how legally binding דרבננ'ס de-rabbonans
are or something like that that is
he's saying helpers presumably it's the community not him
right the whole community right in some way perhaps I hadn't thought
about it much but it's an interesting point so אמר ליה Amar
Lei so אשלח ליה Ashlach Lei so they said oh so should
we go ask him meaning like Rav tried to defend himself by
sort of making an ad hominem attack against the people from לוד
Lod so they said oh so should we actually go send him
a letter and find out what he actually thinks and איכסיף Ichsif
and at that point Rav was actually sort of was embarrassed by
the direction that the line of reasoning had taken that is Rav
did not want to go down an ad hominem attack on a
particular rabbi he really did want to engage at the level of
the legal principles and so he sort of felt he felt bad
that that's how it had gone so now אמר רב Amar Rav
so Rav is now going to try to explain his position so
אמר רב אם הם לא דרשו אנן לא דרשינן Amar Rav im
heim lo darshu ana lo darshinan so if it hadn't been that
they had interpreted the פסוק pasuk this way that is that the
סנהדרין Sanhedrin had declared that this דין דרבנן din de-rabbonan existed even
based on a פסוק pasuk a sort of אסמכתא asmachta to the
פסוק pasuk in Daniel we wouldn't have made this דרשה drasha that
is the דרשה drasha is a good mnemonic if you already know
that the הלכה halacha exists so Rav's point is sort of to
say we never would have understood Daniel to have been saying this
except for the fact that we have a tradition that says it
so Rav is trying to testify to the authenticity and antiquity of
his position והא כתיב Veha Kasiv and doesn't the verse from the
first פרק perek of Daniel everyone's homework go read the first פרק
perek of Daniel
וישם דניאל על לבו אשר לא יתגאל בפת בג המלך ויין משתיו
Vayosem Daniel al libo asher lo yisga'el bepas-bag hamelech uveyayin mishtav
so
Daniel had decided when he was taken to the king's court that
he was not going to eat the bread that was handed out
by the king
ויין משתיו uveyayin mishtav his wine of drinking but it's spelled מלא
malay it's spelled with a יוד yud so
בשתי משתאות הכתוב מדבר bishtei mishta'os hakasuv medaber it sounds like it's
talking about two different types of drink okay אחד משתה יין ואחד
משתה שמן echad mishteh yayin ve'echad mishteh shemen drinking oil and drinking
wine okay משתה mishteh of
יין yayin from משתה mishteh that's what it sounds
like right but one second so the point is Rav admits that
it's not a good דרשה drasha Rav what Rav is saying right
אם הם לא דרשו אנן לא דרשינן im heim lo darshu ana
lo darshinan I would have never made this דרשה drasha that is
I have it on a strong source a received מסורת masoret tradition
that this is how this verse is meant to be understood that
Daniel avoided using the oil of the of the idolatrous king's court
so it must be that that's what it's talking about even though
it doesn't seem evident from the פסוק pasuk okay we still don't
know
why anyway like what the reason is
we're going to get to the reason one second
no I'm just saying at
this point I'm just pointing so far we don't know the reason
רב סבר על לבו שם ולכל ישראל הורה Rav savar al libo
sam u'lechol Yisrael hora Rav thinks that because the פסוק pasuk says
right וישם דניאל על לבו Vayosem Daniel al libo he decided for
himself so Rav says oh על לבו שם al libo sam he
decided it for himself ולכל ישראל הורה u'lechol Yisrael hora and then
he taught that הלכה halacha to everyone that that was a binding
law that is he and his בית דין Beis Din established a
גזרה gezara right and הורה hora is also an interesting word because
it's like a הוראה hora'ah he issued a פסק psak oil is
prohibited right ושמואל סבר על לבו שם ולכל ישראל לא הורה u'Shmuel
savar al libo sam u'lechol Yisrael lo hora Shmuel says it was
a personal position that Daniel adopted for himself but it's not something
that he promulgated and and ruled for the whole so
that means there never
was a גזרה gezara
then so you didn't need
Rebbi to come לבטל levatel it then if there was no no
according to Shmuel there was no גזרה gezara in the time of
Daniel according to Shmuel the problem is לפתן של כלים אסורים liftan
shel keilim asurim right that there's a concern there's a risk that
there will be adulterants that seep into the oil and therefore they
made
a general גזרה gezara
at
some point after Daniel and then and then Rebbi's בית דין Beis
Din said came and said wait a second isn't it נותן טעם
לפגם, noten ta'am lifgam, it's not a problem at all. Okay. So
those are the opinions of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel so far.
Okay. And I know Rabbi Linzer has like a whole thing about
why the first פרק perek of דניאל Daniel is very interesting source
to consider for this.
Okay. Because דניאל Daniel is all about kind of intermixing different communities
and things like that. Okay. ושמן דניאל גזר? V'shemen Daniel gazar? And
was it really Daniel who made the law against
oil? והאמר באלי אבימי נתונה משמי דרב: V'ha'amar Ba'ali Avimi Netuna mishmei
de'Rav: פיתן ושמנה ויינאן ובנותיהן כולן משמונה עשר דבר הן. pitan ushemana
veyeinan uvenoteihen kullan mishmonah asar davar hein. So bread and bread and
oil and wine and quote-unquote their daughters are all those four are
among the
eighteen גזירות gezeirot that were made by בית שמאי Beis Shammai that
one day that בית שמאי Beis Shammai had more members than בית
הלל Beis Hillel and they voted in eighteen גזירות. gezeirot. Okay. וכי
תימא אתא דניאל גזר ולא קיבל? Vechi teima ata Daniel gazar velo
kibeil? So maybe you could say Daniel tried to make the גזירה
gezeirah but the people didn't accept
it. ואתו תלמידי דהלל ושמאי וגזור וקיבל. Va'atu talmidei d'Hillel v'Shammai v'gazur
v'kibeil. And then came a later generation, the students of שמאי Shammai
and הלל Hillel and then they tried to re-establish the same גזירה
gezeirah and it was accepted at that
point. אם כן מאי אסהדותיה דרב? Im kein mai asahaduteih de'Rav? So
then what's the whole point of רב Rav telling me that it
was established in the time of דניאל Daniel if when דניאל Daniel
tried to make this גזירה gezeirah it wasn't accepted? It was only
accepted in the time of the students of הלל Hillel and
שמאי. Shammai. Okay. אלא דניאל גזר עליו בעיר. Ela Daniel gazar alav
ba'ir. So no, דניאל Daniel made a rule against it in urban
settings where there are a lot of people
around. ואתו אינהו וגזור אפילו בשדה. Va'atu inhu v'gazur afilu basadeh. And
then the students of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel saw that this
was becoming a problem even in more rural areas and they extended
the גזירה. gezeirah. Okay, okay, shh, okay, okay. ורבי יהודה הנשיא היכי
מצי למשרא תקנתא דתלמידי שמאי והלל? V'Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi heichi matzi l'mishrei
takanta d'talmidei Shammai v'Hillel? And how could רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi come and permit something which was prohibited by a תקנה, takkanah,
here it's called a תקנה takkanah not גזירה, gezeirah, a תקנה takkanah
of the students of שמאי Shammai and
הלל? Hillel? והתנן אין בית דין יכול לבטל דברי בית דין חבירו
אלא אם כן גדול הימנו בחכמה ובמנין. V'hatnan ein beis din yachol
levatel divrei beis din chaveiro ela im kein gadol heimenu bechochmah uvemnyan.
The same principle we had before, how could רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi abrogate a ruling that was established by the students of
הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai obviously with much greater seniority, greater
sense of setting precedent? So it's still the same problem. ועוד הא
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן? V'od ha amar Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan? And further,
we have a teaching from רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar
Chana quoting רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in ארץ ישראל: Eretz Yisrael: בכל
יכול לבטל בית דין
דברי
בית דין חבירו חוץ משמונה עשר דבר.
bechol yachol levatel beis din divrei
beis
din chaveiro chutz mishmonah asar davar. There is some sort of a
principle or a tradition that every rabbinic law could be repealed except
for those eighteen things which no בית דין beis din could, later
בית דין beis din would repeal, שאפילו יבוא אליהו ובית דינו אין
שומעין לו. she'afilu yavo Eliyahu uveit dino ein shomein lo. That even
if אליהו Eliyahu will come in future times and re-establish the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin in Messianic era and they try to repeal those eighteen laws,
we still nonetheless are not going to listen to them. Which is
very interesting to think why were those eighteen of all things, those
are the ones that בית שמאי Beis Shammai won out over בית
הלל Beis Hillel on one day, why those are sort of permanently
fixed as emblematic of the whole rabbinic system such that we can't
repeal them, but every other גזירה gezeirah from earlier times and later
times could be changed or repealed is a fascinating question we don't
have time for.
And also אליהו Eliyahu also is a בית דין beis din right.
Of course.
Because
we're talking about the institution of the court, right? An individual, דניאל
Daniel can't just come and make a law. אליהו Eliyahu can't just
come and make a law, right? You need a court, it needs
to be through the
בית דין הגדול. Beis Din HaGadol. אל השופט אשר יהיה בימים ההם.
El hashofet asher yihyeh bayamim hahem. It's not through the prophet's prophetic
powers. The רמב"ם Rambam talks about this extensively, that prophets don't have
power to legislate by dint of their prophetic powers, they have only
power to legislate as part of their role on the בית דין
הגדול. Beis Din HaGadol. Most of the prophets served according to רמב"ם's
Rambam's tabulation, which for him is very important. All basically all of
the prophets served as heads of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, of the בית
דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol in their generation. That is, they had
a legislative role as well as a prophetic role and they're kept
separate. Okay, okay. אמר רב משרשיא. Amar Rav Mesharshiya. Yes. So what
is בנותיהם? uvenoteihem?
Well, it's one of the eighteen.
We're going to get to what's בנותיהן. benoteihen. It's the beginning, that's
the main topic of עמוד ב'. amud beis. Okay. אמר רב משרשיא
מה טעם? Amar Rav Mesharshiya mah ta'am? So what's the
reason? הואיל ופשט איסורו ברוב ישראל. Ho'il ufashat issuro berov Yisrael. So
the reason why those eighteen גזירות gezeirot could not be repealed is
because they have spread throughout the whole Jewish people. They are commonly
accepted through the majority of the Jewish people. שמן לא פשט איסורו
ברוב ישראל. Shemen lo pashat issuro berov Yisrael. But the decree against
the oil... the oil at its time was not so popular and
maybe that's why רבי יהודה הנשיא Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi was able to
repeal, not only able to but also wanted to repeal it and
did, because the people weren't keeping it. It was not so popular.
This is one of the 17 out of 18, right? Maybe so
it's maybe 17 out of 18, right? This is one of the
18. If they say that this is one of the 18 and
then it was repealed, that's what seems like our discussion here is,
that is they made 18 גזירות, gezeirot, then רבי Rebbi repealed the
law against the
שמן. shemen. Okay. דאמר רבי שמואל בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן de'amar
Rabbi Shmuel bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan ישיבו רבותינו בדקו על שמן
שלא פשט איסורו ברוב ישראל. yashivu raboteinu badku al shemen shelo pashat
issuro berov Yisrael. The so רבי שמואל בר אבא Rabbi Shmuel bar
Abba quoted רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that our teachers, that is
the, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is maybe, maybe was a direct student
of רבי Rebbi but more likely a student of רבי's Rebbi direct
students. But he says in their generation, meaning in my teachers' time,
they investigated and they found out that the oil, the law against
oil had not been spread throughout the majority of
Israel, וסמכו רבותינו על דברי רבן שמעון בן גמליאל ועל דברי רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק, v'samchu raboteinu al divrei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel v'al
divrei Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok, they relied upon the position of these
two of תנאים, Tannaim, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
and רבי אלעזר בר צדוק Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok who said שהיו
אומרים אין גוזרים גזירה על הציבור אלא אם כן רוב ציבור יכולים
לעמוד בה. shehayu omrim ein gozrim gezeira al hatzibur ela im ken
rov tzibur yecholim la'amod bah. That now there are two different ways
we could translate this: the בית דין beit din cannot decree a
law that the majority of the community cannot uphold or the בית
דין beit din should not decree a law that the majority of
the community cannot uphold. That is, is this a limitation on the
powers of the בית דין beit din or is this just a
recommendation that, hey, watch out, don't make laws that the majority of
the people are going to be violating because then you've just created
people who are sinning for no reason? So if this is a
limitation and it could even be applied post-facto, then what it means
is if there comes a time when there is a rabbinic law
which is no longer being observed by the majority of the Jewish
people,
which is almost every law nowadays,
which to a certain extent, well, maybe who counts as פשט ברוב
ישראל? pashat berov Yisrael? Well, but do we say רוב ישראל כשרים
rov Yisrael kesherim or something, right, people who are otherwise fully observant
but don't observe X, does that mean that X poof vanishes? That
would be a very radical type of application of this principle. Maybe
you would still need, and this again I said is discussed extensively
at the beginning of ביצה, Beitza, maybe you still need judicial action
to apply the principle. That is, this principle may be in effect,
but you would still need a בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol
to come and say, note, we investigated and noticed that the law
of the oil no longer... for sure, that's what he did. Right,
so that's what רבי Rebbi did, meaning it doesn't apply automatically, it's
not poof and the law vanishes, you still need the authority of
the בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol to repeal the law. That
is, they can assess the circumstances and say this is a good
reason to get rid of a law.
No, but can you do it? Like in other words, there's a
couple of competing things going on here. Let's say at some point
the ציבור tzibur was יכול לעמוד בה yechol la'amod bah but then
it can't. Do we then reassess?
Well, it sounds like, I'm not sure. No, what he said was
because, it sounds like לא פשט, lo pashat, it never caught on,
right, it's not like it first caught on and then became unpopular.
So that's another piece of it which is again very important because
then the question is, oh, was it a problem at the time
the law was initially made that they were overreaching, or is the
problem just that we don't want people violating these rabbinic laws and
if we could eliminate them it would be better for the Jewish
people then we get rid of them?
Okay, so would you agree it sounds like the first one?
I think it does sound a bit like the first one, but
I'm not 100% convinced. Okay, so the point is here, so and
that is a minority position, right? That's only quoted as they, they
felt it was necessary to rely upon the position of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and רבי אלעזר בר צדוק, Rabbi
Elazar bar Tzadok, that is these two תנאים Tannaim who held like
this. It sounds like the majority of the תנאים Tannaim did not
hold like this, that you're totally allowed or totally encouraged to make
גזירות gezeirot even if the majority of the community doesn't keep them,
which is also interesting. Okay. שהיו אומרים... shehayu omrim... okay.
Where is
רבי Rebbi in the versus רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel? רבי Rebbi is the, the what? Great-grandson of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? Okay.
Yeah.
So it wasn't that much longer then?
No. No, meaning they articulated some general principle and then רבי Rebbi
comes along, oh, I think this is a good principle to apply
or to institute in this case. Or maybe he's even, I mean
it depends on which רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
it is, it might be רבי's, Rebbi רבי's Rebbi father himself, which
would be even more interesting. Okay.
And then שמאי, Shammai, I'm sorry, and שמאי, Shammai, where is he?
הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai are six generations earlier. You know, they're
200, 300 years before. Yeah.
Okay, so basically it was around for 200 or 300 years and
then the, so within, well and
again it had been around since the time of דניאל Daniel also
at least in abstract or at least בעיר be'ir but not בשדה
basadeh or whatever. Right, we're seeing the Talmudic attempt to parse all
of this, right? We don't see any opinions of תנאים Tannaim being
quoted here. This is all אמוראים Amoraim talking about something in the
משנה Mishna which was just stated והשמן, v'hashemen, right? So actually in
the Tannaitic material we don't have so much about oh when was
it instituted or whatever like they just sort of assume or, or
state clearly like oh there was this law against שמן shemen and
then it got repealed.
Right, but then רבי Rebbi went the whole way. Now as interesting...
Okay, you know what, it's let's keep the part that דניאל Daniel
had בעיר, ba-ir, let's repeal it in the שדה. sadeh. He just
did the whole he did
away with the whole thing. Right. So that's also interesting. שי, Shai,
okay. Last line of ל"ו עמוד א', Lamed Vav Amud Alef, דאמר
רב אדא בר אהבה de-amar Rav Adda bar Ahava מאי קרא, mai
kra, because what's the source in the תנ"ך Tanakh that supports the
idea of this principle that we cannot institute or should not institute
גזרות gezerot which do not catch on in the whole community? The
פסוק pasuk from מלאכי, Malachi, במארה אתם נארים ואותי אתם קובעים הגוי
כולו. bame'era atem ne'arim ve-oti atem kovim hagoy kulo. So the פסוק
pasuk says הגוי כולו, hagoy kulo, the entire nation. It's interesting to
note the first half of the פסוק pasuk as well, right? That
you are cursing me with curses and you're cursing my name, the
entire nation. That is only when the entire nation is cursing against
God. So what's the curse against God? It sounds like a דין
דרבנן din de-rabbanan is in a sense במארה אתם נארים, bame'era atem
ne'arim, right? In some way,
is
God, right, does God like it when we make extra חומרות chumrot
and extra דינים דרבנן dinim de-rabbanan and expand what's prohibited in the
world, or does God not like it so much? So you could
read this, you could make some interesting דרוש drush about this that
maybe actually, right, you know, God would say, "What, why are you
making extra things up? So I said it was fine." Right. But
maybe they, okay, okay. אי איכא גוי כולו. ei
ika goy kulo. רש"י Rashi
says it's interesting, במארה אתם
נארים,
bame'era
atem
ne'arim, if you are מקבל mekabel a גזרה gezerah בארור וקללה, be-arur
u-kelalah, that that's if you
don't uphold it, then it's a curse, right? So that's a way
to read it.
One second. Okay. So
to
me it sounds like he's saying if you are, if you take
accept this upon in your self bindingly as you would... like a
binding acceptance like
the words of the ברית, berit, like בהר גריזים ובהר עיבל. be-Har
Gerizim uve-Har Eival. Exactly. Right. So אי איכא גוי כולו, ei ika
goy kulo, if there's the entire community, אין, in, אי לא, לא,
ei lo, lo, then yes, and if not, no. Okay. נו, Nu,
discussion גופא. gufa. אמר Amar באלי Bali אמר אבימי נתנא משמיה דרב,
amar Bali amar Avimi Natana mishmei de-Rav, so the position אבימי Avimi
quoted, באלי Bali quoted
the opinion of אבימי Avimi quoting רב, Rav, פיתן ושמנן ויינן ובנותיהם,
pitan veshamnan veyenan u-venoteihem, these four things: bread, oil, wine, and quote
unquote their daughters, כולן משמונה עשר דבר הן, kulan mishmonah asar davar
hen, these are among the eighteen decrees of בית שמאי ובית הלל.
Beit Shammai u-Veit Hillel. So מאי היא? mai hi? So, sorry, בנותיהם
מאי היא? benoteihem mai hi? So what is בנותיהם, benoteihem, their daughters,
mean? Okay. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says, גזרו בנותיהם נדות מעריסותן. gazru benoteihem
niddot me-arisotan. So רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says
now we should remember מדאורייתא, mi-de'oraita, the biblical law is that the
laws of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah do not apply to non-Jewish people
at all, except perhaps for a corpse of a non-Jewish person, should
still be מטמא במת, metamei be-met, but basic... and that's even a
debate among the תנאים, Tannaim, but otherwise the laws of טומאה וטהרה
tumah ve-taharah don't apply to non-Jews. Non-Jews are not מקבל טומאה mekabel
tumah at all. If they touch a שרץ, sheretz, if they touch
a נבילה, neveilah, whatever, it doesn't matter. But מדרבנן mi-de-rabbanan there are
multiple types of טומאה tumah which were instituted for non-Jewish people, presumably
to act as a first of all just as sort of to
if we're going to create social separation between Jews based on טומאה
וטהרה tumah ve-taharah then קל וחומר kal va-chomer we should create some
kind of social separation between non-Jews as well regarding those same kind
of concerns. Especially non-Jewish women is what they're talking about. Right. And
particularly here there's a sexual and and female question, which is that
all of the non-Jewish women מעריסותן me-arisotan from their cribs, from the
time that they're infants, are considered to be נדות. niddot. That is,
their טומאת נידה tumat niddah if they touch your food or whatever,
and also there's the concern that whatever prohibited sexual activity there would
be with a non-Jewish woman is compounded with the prohibition of נידה
niddah as well.
Okay. וגניבא משמיה דרב אמר, u-Gneiva mishmei de-Rav amar, so גניבא Gneiva
quoted רב, Rav, אמר כולן משום עבודה כוכבים גזרו בהם. amar kulan
mishum avodah kochavim gazru bahem. These four things are all because of
a problem of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. כי אתא רב אחא בר
אדא אמר רבי יצחק, Ki ata Rav Acha bar Adda amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, so when רב אחא בר אדא Rav Acha bar Adda came
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he quoted רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, גזרו
פיתן משום שמנן. gazru pitan mishum shamnan. They made a law against
bread because of a concern of oil.
Which is interesting, but then you'd think if the oil goes then
the bread should go too.
Okay, so we're going to one second. So he said גזרו פיתן
משום שמנן. gazru pitan mishum shamnan. So מאי אולמיה דשמן מפת? mai
ulmeih de-shemen mi-pat? Why is oil a stronger connection than bread? אלא
על פיתן ושמנן משום יינן. ela al pitan veshamnan mishum yenan. No,
oil and bread are both because of wine, that is there's some
connection, either the oil is in some way similar to the wine
or bread because if you're going to drink together you're going to
come to eat together. Whatever... sorry, if you're going to eat together
you're going to come to drink together and you put oil in
the food or you put oil on the bread or whatever and
it's going to come you're going to have a glass of wine
as well. ועל יינן משום בנותיהם, ve-al yenan mishum benoteihem, and because
of wine because of a concern of quote unquote their daughters. ועל
בנותיהם משום דבר אחר, ve-al benoteihem mishum davar acher, and because of
their daughters for some other reason.
That's interesting, you would think because of daughters cause you're just worried
that's just...
Wait wait you thought that because of daughters because you're just worried
that's enough isn't that reason enough? Okay well one second ועל דבר
אחר משום דבר אחר v'al davar acher mishum davar acher and something
else because of something else that is these are rabbinic euphemisms right
if you look in רש״י Rashi על דבר אחר שלא הוזכר כאן
גזר משום דבר אחר לא משום עבודת אלילים לקמן מפרש לה al
davar acher shelo huzkar kan gazar mishum davar acher lo mishum avodat
elilim l'kaman mefaresh lah so that the דבר אחר davar acher the
first דבר אחר davar acher sounds like it's עבודה זרה avoda zara
and the second דבר אחר davar acher well then what they made
a גזירה gezeira against עבודה זרה avoda zara because of something else?
I don't even know what the something else. So we're going to
see.
But in some places right דבר אחר davar acher could mean all
sorts of things. דבר אחר davar acher could mean pork, דבר אחר
davar acher could mean sex, דבר אחר davar acher could mean עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, דבר אחר davar acher could mean צרעת, tzara'at, it
could mean lots of different things in lots of different places. צרעת
tzara'at that's a discussion right the eating fish and meat that were
roasted together is says because of דבר אחר davar acher I think.
I think so. So it's considered צרעת tzara'at as well. Okay.
So משום בנותיהן. mishum benoteihem. So בנותיהם דאורייתא היא benoteihem d'oraita hi
wait a second isn't the prohibition of a Jewish man having a
marrying a non-Jewish woman a דאורייתא? d'oraita? דכתיב לא תתחתן בם. dichtiv
lo titchaten bam. You're not allowed to marry them. So דאורייתא זיין
אומות d'oraita zayin umot the דאורייתא d'oraita only applies to the seven
original Canaanite nations קיני פריזי אמורי חוי יבוסי Kenini Prizi Emori Chivi
Yevusi right only those nations אבל שאר עובדי כוכבים לא aval shear
ovdei kochavim lo there's actually no דאורייתא d'oraita prohibition against a Jewish
man marrying an idolatrous
woman מדאורייתא. mid'oraita. ואתו אינהו וגזרו אפילו דשאר עובדי כוכבים v'atu inhu
v'gazru afilu deshear ovdei kochavim and then later the Rabbis came and
made a law against other other idolatrous peoples as well. ולרבי שמעון
בן יוחי דאמר כי יסיר את בנך מאחרי u'l'Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai
d'amar ki yasir et bincha me'achari
but doesn't the פסוק pasuk say there's a concern that she the
wife will turn your son away from me that is that a
Jewish man who marries a non-Jewish woman will be seduced to worship
an idolatrous religion it will be turned away from from God לרבות
כל המסירות l'rabot kol hamasirot
and רבי שמעון בן יוחי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai says that that
means it comes to include any idolatrous woman because there's the same
risk
with any idolatrous woman.
Right that the דאורייתא d'oraita should include all idolatrous women מה איכא
למימר mai ika l'meimar so how can we respond to רבי שמעון
בן יוחי? Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai? אלא דאורייתא אישות דרך חתנות ela
d'oraita ishut derech chatnut the דאורייתא d'oraita principle is if you get
married for the sake of marriage for the sake of a long-term
relationship ואתו אינהו וגזרו אפילו דרך זנות v'atu inhu v'gazru afilu derech
znut and the later Rabbis came and prohibited sexual relationships between Jewish
men and non-Jewish women even if it were only for casual sexual
relationship not marriage because presumably if you're only interacting for a brief
sexual encounter there's less of a risk that this long-term relationship is
going to result in you being seduced to worship עבודה זרה avoda
zara because you're not emotionally invested or you're not in a relationship
for many years that's a lower risk. But wait a second זנות
נמי בבית דינו של שם גזרו znut nami b'beit dino shel Shem
gazru but there's a universal is very interesting בית דינו של שם
Beit Dino shel Shem we're going back way back in history רב
אלחנן וסרמן Rav Elchanan Wasserman in his קונטרס דברי סופרים Kuntras Divrei
Sofrim talks about the principles of דרבנן drabbanan law he talks a
lot about what does it mean בית דינו של שם Beit Dino
shel Shem the the rabbinic laws that were instituted at the time
of Shem right after the flood sort of a sense universal דרבנן
drabbanan laws right we have מצוות בני נח mitzvot b'nei Noach which
we in some way are divinely decreed universal law and then there's
בית דינו של שם Beit Dino shel Shem there's rabbinic laws of
of the seven מצוות בני נח mitzvot b'nei Noach which is very
interesting. So the בית דין Beit Din of Shem instituted the law
against זנות znut that is there's a prohibition against any kind of
promiscuous sexual activity דכתיב ויאמר יהודה הוציאוה ותשרף dichtiv vayomer Yehuda hotziuha
vetisaref because when Tamar was found to be pregnant during a period
when she was presumably widowed and not married there
so יהודה Yehuda said the punishment should be that she should be
killed. So it sounds like there was a law against her having
a promiscuous sexual relationship at that time. אלא דאורייתא עובד כוכבים הבא
על בת ישראל ela d'oraita oved kochavim haba al bat Yisrael no
the דאורייתא d'oraita law against חתנות chatnut against intermarriage or inter right
intermarriage with idolaters is a idolatrous man who has a relationship with
a Jewish woman דמשכא בתריה d'mashcha batrei because he brings her after
him into his home into his environment into his
culture אבל ישראל הבא על עובדת כוכבים לא. aval Yisrael haba al
ovedet kochavim lo.
Wait
sorry even from the שבעה עממים? shiva amamim?
It sounds like this is where it's taken even from the שבעה
עממים. shiva amamim. ואתו אינהו וגזרו אפילו ישראל הבא על עובדת כוכבים
v'atu inhu v'gazru afilu Yisrael haba al ovedet kochavim and the דרבנן
drabbanan law came and adjusted it and said no we should also
make a law against a Jewish man with non-Jewish woman. Okay.
Just for even זנות znut all this is just זנות znut purposes
right or?
No the זנות znut was instituted by Shem and now we're talking
about either way meaning it's not that the דאורייתא d'oraita דרבנן drabbanan
split is between אישות ishut and חתנות chatnut the difference will be
between man
She
was a married woman though, so wouldn't it have been this example?
But her husband died. Her husband. At the time she wasn't married
she was יבמה לשוק, Yevama Lashuk, she was her husband had died
and his brother was supposed to, right, יבום, Yibum, but had not.
Okay, ואתו אינהו גזרו אפילו ישראל על עובדת כוכבים? ve-atu inhu gazru
afilu Yisrael al ovedet kochavim? ישראל הבא על עובדת כוכבים, Yisrael ha-ba
al ovedet kochavim, but wait a second, a Jewish man with a
non-Jewish woman הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai he is. That's not
a דרבנן, de-Rabbanan, that's הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. דאמר מר
הבועל ארמית קנאין פוגעין בו de-amar Mar ha-boel Aramit kana'in pog'in bo
because דאמר מר, de-amar Mar, right, is anonymous teaching, at least as
it's quoted here. If a Jewish man has a sexual, and here
it's very crude, right, הבועל ארמית, ha-boel Aramit, it's not even like
you marry her or something like that, it's really about the sexual
act, הבועל ארמית, ha-boel Aramit, if you have a sexual relationship with
a non-Jewish or idolatrous woman קנאין פוגעין בו. kana'in pog'in bo. There's
no capital punishment for that, but anyone who can interrupt you and
take their lives into, take the law into their own hands to
interrupt you will kill you in order to stop you. So we
say דאורייתא בפרהסיא וכמעשה שהיה. de-Oraita be-farhesya u-ke-ma'aseh she-hayah. It's learned from
the story of Pinchas. So the דאורייתא de-Oraita principles only if it's
actually taking place in public like the story of Zimri where they
actually were in the front of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. I mean
people, some people often talk about oh we're so uncomfortable with what
Pinchas... think about what Zimri was doing. Zimri was having a public
sexual relationship with an idolatrous woman right in front of אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed, right in the center of the camp in the משכן
Mishkan in front of Moshe, in front of the זקנים, Zekenim, right?
So obviously Pinchas had to stop him. I'm sorry wait, you said
דאורייתא.
de-Oraita. I thought we said דאורייתא de-Oraita was גוי הבא על בת
ישראל. goy ha-ba al bat Yisrael.
No, this is now we're talking about Jewish, so we said the
דאורייתא de-Oraita which is explicit in the Torah, at least they said
oh that's גוי הבא על בת ישראל, goy ha-ba al bat Yisrael,
that's a non-Jewish man with a Jewish woman, and a Jewish man
with a non-Jewish woman is הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai which
is learned from the story of Pinchas which is this case. So
when he says דאורייתא de-Oraita
he doesn't mean דאורייתא, de-Oraita, he just means הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai which we just said.
Here it sounds like דאורייתא de-Oraita means הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha le-Moshe
mi-Sinai, right. בפרהסיא, be-farhesya, in public, כמעשה שהיה, ke-ma'aseh she-hayah, like the
case of Pinchas. By the way it's strange, usually
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai does not include something which could
be learned explicitly from a פסוק. pasuk. So it's also strange, right?
The Pinchas story is taken as evidence for this law being in
effect but it does not teach the law. It's not explicit in
the story that it was the law because if the punishment is
קנאין פוגעין בו, kana'in pog'in bo, it's take the law into your
own hands, it can't be legally demonstrative to use a case of
someone taking the law into their own hands. Okay.
קנאין פוגעין בו, דאורייתא בפרהסיא כמעשה שהיה ואתו אינהו גזרו אפילו בצינעא.
kana'in pog'in bo, de-Oraita be-farhesya ke-ma'aseh she-hayah ve-atu inhu gazru afilu be-tzina.
And the rabbis came and made a law against even in private.
בצינעא נמי בית דינו של חשמונאי גזרו. be-tzina nami beit dino shel
Chashmonai gazru. But wait a second,
okay, it couldn't have been the students of Shamai and Hillel who
made that law because that was already prohibited in the time of
the
חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר
בית דינו של חשמונאי גזרו.
de-ki ata Rav Dimi amar beit dino shel
Chashmonai gazru.
So
when Rav Dimi came, he said that the בית דין beit din
of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim made the law against ישראל הבא על עובדת
כוכבים Yisrael ha-ba al ovedet kochavim חייב משום נשגא. chayav mishum nashga.
So what is נשגא? nashga? נדה, שפחה, גויה ואשת איש. Niddah, Shifcha,
Goya ve-Eshet Ish. Four, it violates four different prohibitions, at least at
a rabbinic level, violates a prohibition against נדה, Niddah, violates שפחה Shifcha
that she's considered to be a slave woman, גויה Goya that she's
a non-Jewish woman, and אשת איש Eshet Ish that she's...
Even if she's not married?
Even if she's not married. They sort of put it in a
rabbinic category of all four of these
violations: נדה, שפחה, גויה, אשת איש. Niddah, Shifcha, Goya, Eshet Ish. כי
אתא רבין אמר משום נשגא, ki ata Ravin amar mishum nashga, when
Ravin came he taught a slightly different version of the same teaching:
משום נשגא mishum nashga which is נדה, שפחה, גויה Niddah, Shifcha, Goya
and זונה. Zona. Not אשת איש Eshet Ish that she's a married
woman.
Because she might not be.
Because
she might not be, but she certainly is in a promiscuous and
overly permissive sexual relation. Okay, okay, I can't teach if you're crying,
okay?
Can you please... she's just disappointed. She's looking at
him like, why did you bring her? Master is very disappointed. She
wants me all...
oh okay.
I know because you're getting hungry because it's late. Okay.
כי גזרו בית דינו של חשמונאי ביאה, ki gazru beit dino shel
Chashmonai bi'ah, the בית דין beit din of חשמונאי Chashmonai made a
law against specifically a sexual act. אבל ייחוד לא, aval yichud lo,
but they did not prohibit ייחוד. yichud. They didn't prohibit a Jewish
man with a non-Jewish woman to have ייחוד yichud together. ואתו אינהו,
ve-atu inhu, and the students of Beit Shamai and Beit Hillel later
came גזרו אפילו ייחוד. gazru afilu yichud. They made a law even
against ייחוד. yichud. ייחוד נמי בית דינו של דוד גזר. yichud nami
beit dino shel David gazar. But wait a second, the... So we're
going back in time again, back to— I mean,
no matter what, there was there was an earlier time that this
was already thought of.
What, things were already thought of, right? So David's בית דין Beis
Din made a law against ייחוד yichud with a non-Jewish woman, דאמר
רב יהודה de'amar Rav Yehuda באותה שעה גזרו על ייחוד be'osah sha'ah
gazru al yichud because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda quoted that at that
time, that is the time of when Amnon raped his sister Tamar.
Ah, so the question is what was the scope of David's decree?
But whatever it was, David's בית דין Beis Din made a law
against ייחוד yichud to prevent against violations of עריות arayos it sounds
like. אמרי התם Amrei hatam ייחוד דבת ישראל. yichud de'bas Yisrael. Exactly
Michael's point, that at that time they only made a prohibition against
against Jewish man with a with a Jewish woman, אבל ייחוד דעובד
כוכבים לא, aval yichud de'oved kochavim lo, they didn't make any law
against ייחוד yichud with a non-Jewish woman, presumably because they felt that
there should be less— there was no concern. ואתו אינהו גזרו אפילו
ייחוד דעובד כוכבים. ve'atu inhu gazru afilu yichud de'oved kochavim. And then
the students of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel came, or the חשמונאים,
Chashmonaim, sorry, came and made a law against ייחוד yichud with... oh,
you're right, at least it says— oh, you're right, because the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim made a law against ביאה. biah. Sorry, you're right, it's the
students of שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel came and made the law
against ייחוד yichud with עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. Okay.
ייחוד דבת ישראל דאורייתא היא. yichud de'bas Yisrael de'oraisa hi. But ייחוד
yichud with a Jewish woman is already a דאורייתא de'oraisa problem. You're
telling me that it was instituted by David's בית דין? Beis Din?
It was a דאורייתא de'oraisa problem. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון
בן יהוצדק, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan taught quoting רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak,
רמז לייחוד מן התורה מניין? remez le'yichud min ha'Torah minayin? How do
we know that there's a hint to the idea of ייחוד yichud
in the Torah? It's a רמז. remez. It's a רמז, remez, right,
what does רמז remez mean? Does רמז remez mean it's an אסמכתא?
asmachta? Does רמז remez mean it's a real דאורייתא? de'oraisa? Whatever, שנאמר
shene'emar כי יסיתך אחיך בן אמך. Ki yasitcha achicha ben imecha. בן
אם מסית בן אב
אינו מסית?
ben em
mesit
ben av eino
mesit? So the פסוק pasuk says regarding seemingly a discussion of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, not a problem of sexual relationships, that if your
brother who is your mother's son seduces you... but wait a second,
בן אם מסית. ben em mesit. Does your maternal brother seduce you
to worship idols but not your paternal brother? אלא בן מתייחד עם
אמו ella ben misyached im imo ואין אחר מתייחד עם כל עריות
שבתורה. ve'ein acher misyached im kol arayos she'ba'Torah. But a son can
be secluded with his mother, but no one else is allowed to
be secluded with other of the עריות, arayos, that is any of
the other עריות. arayos. Okay, I'm going to have to stop here
because my daughter is being very fussy. I'm sorry. Have a great
day everyone, we'll pick up here tomorrow.